Thank you, Sister Wan'er
고맙네, 완아 동생
Risking yourself to save us, mother and son
우리 모자를 구하기 위해 위험을 무릅쓰다니
A transaction
거래일 뿐입니다
Each has their needs
서로 원하는 바가 있겠지요
But I cannot go with you
근데 난 동생을 따라갈 수 없네
Why?
무슨 이유입니까?
I am Prince Ning's
난 영왕이
Most important trump card to threaten Your Highness
전하를 협박하는 중요한 패일세
If the prince and I both disappear
나와 세자가 함께 사라지면
Prince Ning will search everywhere
영왕은 어떻게든
And find us
우릴 찾아내려 할 거야
By then
그렇게 되면
Not only will we not be safe
우리 목숨도 부지하지 못하지만
But you will also lose your life
자네마저 목숨을 잃게 돼
Only if I stay
내가 남아 있어야
Will Prince Ning think his trump card remains
영왕은 자기의 패가 여전히 있다고 여길 걸세
Take the prince away
세자를 데리고 가서
Take good care of him
잘 돌봐주게
Thank you
고맙네
March of the 24th year of Yuankang
원강 24년 3월
Prince of Jin Sikong Yao led a great army to attack the capital Nandu
진왕 사공요는 대군을 이끌고 도성인 남도를 들이칩니다
Facing this northern expedition army
이 북벌 대군 앞에서
Nandu's defenders were powerless to resist
남도성의 수비군은 저항할 힘을 잃고
After one day
하루 만에
Nandu fell
남도성은 함락됩니다
Xie Xuan
사현
Where is your sister?
네 누이는
Where is she?
어디 있느냐?
I'm asking you, where is your sister?
네 누이 어디 있냐고!
Miss
아가씨
Why do you look so worried?
왜 그렇게 시름이 가득해요?
Father insists I marry a prince
아버지가 날 왕야에게 시집 보내려 해
I know
아버지가 어떤 생각을 하시는지는 알지만
But I've never even met this Prince of Jin
난 그 진왕이란 분을 한 번도 뵌 적이 없어
I really don't want to marry so blindly
이렇게 시집가고 싶지는 않았는데
How about
아니면
I write you a note
내가 증서라도 하나 써 드리겠소
Owed to my wife
부인에게 빚진
Willow picking at Ba
"파상에서 버들가지 꺾기"
Flower viewing at Yong'an
"영안에서 꽃구경하기"
Kill
죽여라
This is just my letter home
이건 집에서 온 편지인데
Why was it opened?
누가 뜯어본 것이냐?
This edict is fake
이 조서는 가짜야
First wish
첫 번째 소원은
Long live my husband
낭군님이 오래오래 사는 것
Second wish
두 번째 소원은
The prince always healthy
세자가 늘 건강하기를
Third wish
세 번째 소원은
Become swallows on the beam
대들보에 날아드는 제비가 되어
Year after year
해마다 세월이 지나도
Always together
늘 서로를 볼 수 있기를
Ruolan
약란
Yong'an flowers
영안꽃
This debt
이 빚은
I cannot collect
돌려받지 못하겠구나
Ruolan
약란
Prince of Jin Sikong Yao
진왕 사공요는
Seeing me
짐을 보고도
Why don't you kneel?
무릎 꿇지 않느냐!
Drag him down for me
저놈을 끌어내려라!
How dare you
무엄하다!
You
너희
It was you
너였지?
Who drove Ruolan to death
약란을 죽음으로 몰아넣은 게
Sister-in-law
제수씨는
Sister-in-law, to avoid becoming
제수씨는 협박의 빌미가 되지 않기 위해
Already took her own life first
스스로 목숨을 끊은 거야
It was you
바로 너야!
Your ambition
바로 너의 야심이
Killed her
네 부인을 죽게 한 거다!
What?
왜 그래?
Thinking how to kill me?
나를 어떻게 죽일지 생각하느냐?
To ease the guilt in your heart?
그렇게 해야 네 죄책감이 풀릴 것 같으냐?
Let me think
어디 보자...
How will historians record you?
사관은 너를 어떻게 기록할까?
Brothers fighting
형제끼리 싸우고
Killing brother to seize the throne
형을 죽이고 황위를 빼앗았다!
Yao'er
요야
Yao'er, stop
멈추거라
Your elder brother spared you once
그때 네 형이 너를 한 번 살려주지 않았느냐
Mother begs you
어미가 이렇게 빈다
Spare him this time
이번 한 번만 형을 용서해 다오
You are flesh and blood brothers
너희는 핏줄을 나눈 친형제 아니더냐
Yao'er
요야